<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Interest of money mistaken, or, A treatise proving that the abatement of interest is the effect and not the cause of the riches of a nation and that six per cent is a proportionable interest to the present condition of this kingdom.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45942</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12820281</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94198</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961781</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I266A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8986</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12820281</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45942)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 385:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Interest of money mistaken, or, A treatise proving that the abatement of interest is the effect and not the cause of the riches of a nation and that six per cent is a proportionable interest to the present condition of this kingdom.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Interest rates --  Netherlands.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Interest rates --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Commerce.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94198:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94198:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Interest of Money Mistaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR A Treatise, Proving, that the Abatement of INTEREST IS THE EFFECT And not the CAUSE Of the Riches of a NATION, AND THAT SIX PER CENT.</p>
            <p>Is a Proportionable <hi>Interest</hi> to the present condition of this KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1668.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:94198:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94198:2"/>
            <head>Interest of Money mistaken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALthough I hope I shall always have too great a love for my Country, to design the opposing, or discouraging any thing, that may tend to the profit of it; acknowledging, that nothing can be more morally commendable, in men, then indeavours to advance the publike good; Yet having perused a short Treatise late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly published by <hi>I. C.</hi> pleading for the bringing down of <hi>Interest</hi> from Six to Four <hi>per Cent.</hi> as not only being the Intetest of our Nation, but that upon which it puts the whole stress, of the prosperity of any <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>Country;</hi> And not finding that satisfaction in it, as I expected, from a thing writ with so much pretended ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; I shall desire leave of the Author to examine his grounds, and arguments, and that with a love to my Native Country, equal to his own, without having any private interest to my self in it.</p>
            <p>The Treatise begins, with an observation of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious increase of Trade and Riches in the <hi>Ʋnited Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> for which he gives 15 Reasons, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in a Suppliment four more, which are as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>They have in their greatest</hi> Councils of State and War, <hi>trading Merchants that have lived abroad in most parts of the world; who have not only the Theoreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Knowledge, but the Practical Experience of Trade, by whom Laws and Orders are contrived, and Peaces with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94198:3"/> Forreign Princes projected, to the great advantage of their Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Their Law of</hi> Gavel-kind, <hi>whereby all their Children possess an equal share of their Fathers estates after their decease, and so are not left to wrastle with the world in their youth, with inconsiderable assistance of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, as most of our youngest Sons of Gentlemen in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>are, who are bound Apprentices to Merchants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Their exact making of all their Native Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and packing of their</hi> Herrings, Codfish, <hi>and all other Commodities, which they send abroad in great quantities; the consequence whereof is, That the repute of their sad Commodities abroad, continues always good, and the Buyers will accept of them by the marks, without opening; whereas the Fish which our</hi> English <hi>make in</hi> Newfound-Land <hi>and</hi> New-England, <hi>and</hi> Herrings <hi>at</hi> Yarmouth, <hi>often prove false and deeeitfully made, and our</hi> Pilchards <hi>from the</hi> West-Country <hi>false packed; sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom containing the quantity for which the Hogsheads are marked in which they are packed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Their giving great incouragement and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities to the Inventors of New Manufactures, and the Discoverers of any New Mysteries in Trade, and to those that shal bring the Commodities of other Nations first in use and practice among them; for which the Author never goes without his due Reward allowed him at the Publique Charge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Their contriving and building of great Ships to sail with smal charge, and not above one third of what we are at, for Ships of the same Burthen in</hi> England; <hi>and compelling their said Ships (being of smal force) to sail al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in Fleets, to which in all times of danger they allow</hi> Convey.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94198:3"/>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Their parcimonious and thrifty Living, which is so extraordinary, that a Merchant of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand pound estate with them, will scarce spend so much</hi> per annum, <hi>as one of fifteen hundred pounds Estate in</hi> London.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>The education of their Children, as well Daughters as Sons; all which, be they of never so great quality or estate; they always take care to bring up to write perfect good hands, and to have the full knowledge and use of Arithmetick and Merchants Accompts; the well understanding and practice whereof, doth strangely infuse into most that are the owners of that quality, of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sex, not only an ability for Commerce of all kinds, but a strong aptitude, love, and delight in it; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the women are as knowing therein as the men, it doth incourage their husbands to hold on in their Trades to their dying days, knowing the capacity of their wives to get in their Estates, and carry on their Trades after their Deaths: whereas if a Merchant in</hi> England <hi>arrive at any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Estate, he commonly withdraws his Estate from Trade, before he comes near the confines of old Age; recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that if God should call him out of the world, while the main of his Estate is engaged abroad in Trade, he must lose one third of it, through the unexperience and unapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of his Wife to such Affairs, and so it usually falls out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, <hi>The lowness of their</hi> Customs, <hi>and the heighth of their</hi> Excise, <hi>which is certainly the most equal and indifferent</hi> Tax <hi>in the world, and least prejudicial to to any People, as might be made appear were it the subject of this discourse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>The careful providing for, and employment of their poor, which it is easie to demonstrate can never be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94198:4"/> done in</hi> England <hi>comparatively to what it is with them, while it's left to the care of every Parish io look after their own only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>Their use of BANKS, which are of so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence advantage to them, that some, not without good grounds, have estimated the Profit of them to the Publick to amount to at least one million of pounds</hi> sterling per an.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <hi>Their</hi> Toleration in different Opinions in matters of Religion; <hi>by reason whereof many</hi> indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious People <hi>of other Countries,</hi> that dissent from the Established Government of their own Churches, resort to them with their Families and Estates, and after a few years cohabitation with them, become of the same Common interest.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, <hi>Their</hi> Law-Merchant, <hi>By which all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies between Merchants and Tradesmen are decided in three or four days time, and that not at the fortieth part</hi> (I might say in many cases not the hundredth part) <hi>of the charge they are with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, <hi>The Law that is in use among them for</hi> transferrence of Bills for Debt <hi>from one man to another: this it of extraordinary advantage to them in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, by means whereof they can turn their stocks twice or thrice in Trade, for once that we can in</hi> England: <hi>for that having sold our Forreign Goods here, we cannot buy again to advantage, till we are possest of our Money, which it may be we shal be six, nine, or twelve months in recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: And if what we sell be considerable, it is a good man's work all the year to be following Vintners, and Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers for Money. Whereas, were the Law for trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Bills in practise with us, we could presently after sale of our Goods. dispose of our Bills, and close up our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts.
<pb facs="tcp:94198:4"/> To do which, the advantage, ease, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations it would be to Trade, is so great, that none but Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants that have lived where that custom is in use, can value to its due proportion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourteenthly, <hi>Their keeping up</hi> Publick Registers <hi>of all Lands and Houses, Sold or Mortgaged, whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chargeable Law-suits are prevented, and the securities of Lands and Houses rendred indeed, such as we common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call them</hi> Real Securities.</p>
            <p>Fifteenthly, The Lowness of Interest of Money with them, <hi>which in peaceable times exceeds not three</hi> per cent. Per Annum: <hi>and is now, during this War with</hi> England, <hi>not above four</hi> per cent. <hi>at most.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The four other reasons in the suppliments are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Although they have no Law expresly limiting Interest at present, yet they have other Laws which we cannot arrive to, which do effect the same thing among them, and would do the like among us, if we could have them: One whereof, is, their ascertaining</hi> Real Securities <hi>by their</hi> Publique Registers: <hi>for we see evidently Money is not so much wanting in</hi> England, <hi>as</hi> Securities, <hi>which men accompt Infallible; a remarkable instance whereof is; the</hi> East-India Company, <hi>who can and do take up what money they please, for four</hi> per cent. <hi>at any time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Their constitution of</hi> Banks <hi>and</hi> Lumbards, <hi>whereby private persons that have but tollerable credit, may be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed at easie rates from the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Their</hi> Law for transferring Bills of Debt, <hi>menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the beginning of this Discourse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Which is a Custom, and in effect may be here to our purpose accompted as a Law, is the extraordinary Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity used in all their</hi> Publique Affairs, <hi>which in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94198:5"/> greatest</hi> Extremities <hi>have been such, as not to compel them to give above four</hi> per cent. <hi>for the loan of money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having premised these reasons, he notwithstanding puts upon that of <hi>Interest</hi> being at three <hi>per Cent.</hi> the whole stress, And because he cannot say, that ever <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> was by Law brought under six <hi>per Cent.</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> he adds in his Suppliment, three Laws, they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, which, together with their frugality, he affirms, without any reason or proof given for it, is equivolent to the stating of <hi>Interest</hi> by Law, at 3. <hi>per. Cent.</hi> (to wit) <hi>Publick Registers, Banks and Lumbards,</hi> and <hi>the transferring Bills of Debt,</hi> But according to my reason, he ought to have rancked these last, with his 15 former reasons, of the increase of their Trade, and Riches, the rest of their good laws and orders, having their proportionable Influence upon <hi>Interest</hi> as well as they, and I must deny that these last Laws mentioned in his Suppliment are equivolent to a stinted <hi>Interest by Law,</hi> with us; because in <hi>Holland</hi> they have power to take what <hi>Interest</hi> they can get, which if they had a law stating their <hi>Interest</hi> as with us, they could not do.</p>
            <p>But being desirous, to deal as Ingeniously with the Author, as is possible, I shal reduce his discourse to three assertions, which he seems to me, positively to maintain,</p>
            <p>First, <hi>That Interest being brought down from six to four</hi> per Cent. <hi>at present, and hereafter to three, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone certainly increase the trade and riches of this Kingdom, as</hi> Page 7 &amp; 10.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That Interest being lessened (as abovesaid) Land will immediately after the passing such a Law, yeild</hi> 30 <hi>years purchase at least, so that the Nobility and Gentry</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94198:5"/> may presently reckon their estates doubled, and write instead of <hi>fifty, one hundred pounds upon all they have,</hi> Pag. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In his Suppliment he adds, <hi>that the matter in</hi> England <hi>is prepared for an abatement of Interest, and that it cannot be long obstructed, for that Nature will have its course.</hi> Pag. the 17.</p>
            <p>If the truth of these assertions, to which I shall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, had been made out, they would have carryed so much of publick good with them, as would have stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all mens mouths, and made the greatest <hi>Ʋsurers</hi> asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, to have spoke against them; for who could have been so impudent, as to have opposed the doubling the estates of our Nation, when it is as easily done, as said, the matter of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> being so prepared for it, as he averrs, that there wants nothing but the word, <hi>let it be done,</hi> but our condition in this point, not seeming at all to me so clear, as it doth to him, I think it no hard task, to answer his arguments, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow his foundation.</p>
            <p>If after giving his first 14, and afterwards 4 supplimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>reasons,</hi> besides that of <hi>Interest,</hi> with some others, which might have been added, for the Increase of the <hi>Holland</hi> Trade, and Riches, he had concluded, that when we should find our selves under such circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we should find <hi>Interest</hi> to fall naturally of it self, to 4 and 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> as the effects of those circumstances, I should have agreed with him; but without them, to fall <hi>Interest</hi> by a law to 4 and 3 <hi>per. Cent.</hi> as the thing which alone will make us full of Trade, Riches, and in both, able to ballance <hi>Holland,</hi> as he averrs it will, I deny, affirming, that to do what he propounds, is to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94198:6"/> force nature, which he grants will not be forced, and if the matter in <hi>England,</hi> is so prepared for an abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Interest,</hi> that it cannot be long obstructed, as he saith it is, we need no law for stating it, for nature will have its course with us, as well as in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and he cannot instance, in any Country, where by a Law, <hi>Interest</hi> is set under 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and nature is best let alone unforced.</p>
            <p>To prove his first assertion, <hi>that the lowness of</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest <hi>is not the effect, but the cause of trade and riches,</hi> he argues from the greatness of our present trade, to what it was before <hi>An.</hi> 1545. that no <hi>Interest</hi> was set at all, as also from the Increasing of it since, as <hi>Interest</hi> hath by degrees, been brought lower and lower, and makes his observation, that from <hi>An.</hi> 1600 to 1635. there was an Increase of ten for one, in <hi>Merchants Estates,</hi> upon the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and that from the falling of <hi>Interest</hi> from 8 to 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> there hath been a further increase of 10 for one, in <hi>Merchants Estates</hi> Pag. 7. After this, he troubles himself to prove our present condition as to Riches, to be much greater, then formerly, which he needed not have done, every one granting it: But to shew, how subject he is to mistake, I shal deny his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, of <hi>the Nobilities wearing Doublets with Canvas backs,</hi> to be any proof at all, of our poverty then, and our riches now, or any thing more than the fashion or humour of those times: for to all that is versed in anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, it is well known, that our <hi>Nobility</hi> was abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly greater formerly, then now they are, and that their declining hath given rise to the general riches of the Kingdom, more then the abatement of <hi>Interest:</hi> and if I would follow the Authors method, in, arguing; I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94198:6"/> might better prove our present poverty, and former riches, from our Noblemens travelling antiently, with 100 servants and upwards, whereas now they travel, with 5 or 6. and some times fewer, then he our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer poverty, and present riches, by Doublets with Canvas backs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To prove the fall of <hi>Interest</hi> to be the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cause of our riches, he instanceth in the late im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of land in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently imposeth (as if it made for him) that by asking the question, what <hi>Interest</hi> any Country pays, it may by the answer be resolved, that according to the more or lesser <hi>Interest</hi> that they pay, the richer or poorer they are, bringing <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> for examples of poverty, and <hi>France</hi> with <hi>Italy</hi> for riches: These two are all the reasons that I can find, he brings for proving his first assertion, which in truth are none at all, but the effects of other Circumstances, as shall in due place appear:</p>
            <p>Now, he sets up some objections, and then answers them: but if I prove that <hi>Interest</hi> being reduced to a <hi>medium</hi> (as I shall hereafter make 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> appear to be) the falling of it lower will not benefit, but in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral prejudice the Nation, then taking notice of his objections and answers will be needless, and therefore shall only observe his answer to that Objection, That, <hi>if Interest should be fallen to</hi> 4 per Cent. <hi>the</hi> Dutch <hi>would call home their Money;</hi> to which he answers, That, <hi>if they should, it would be the better for us,</hi> Because, saith he, <hi>the Borrower is always a slave to the Lender:</hi> which reason being no more, in the case of <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> then it lies in that of <hi>English,</hi> and <hi>English;</hi> amounts to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94198:7"/> no less then the Condemning all borrowing, and lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and to the discovering his design, of ingrossing all trade, into the hands of a few rich Merchants, who have Money enough of their own to Trade with, to the excluding all young men, that wants it:</p>
            <p>After his Objections, and Answers, he comes to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerate all sorts, that wlll be the better by the fall of <hi>Interest,</hi> but herein he proves nothing, but beggs the question, as he usually doth, in positively concluding, that the law for abatement being made, trade will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately increase, lands will be double in value, and consequently the <hi>King, Nobility, Gentry, Merchants, Tradesmen, Farmers, Clothiers, Marriners, Porters, Pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> all will be the better, and that we shall by this means, produce <hi>Samsons</hi> and <hi>Goliahs</hi> in stock, subtlety, and experience, to coap with our adversaries, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, a very plausible imposition; and I hope, though the Gentleman wants arguments to prove, that it must necessarily be so, he wisheth it would be so:</p>
            <p>Now he comes to give two Instances against <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest</hi> at 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and for the fall of it, one from old <hi>Audleys</hi> observing that 100 <hi>l.</hi> at <hi>Interest,</hi> at 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> will in seventy years come to one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds, wherein I affirm he is no less mistaken then in other things: The other, that the <hi>Sugar-Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> by reason of the lowness of <hi>Interest,</hi> can afford to give greater rates for our <hi>Barbadoes Sugars,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the charge of carrying them into <hi>Holland,</hi> and grow richer by their trades, than ours can do that buys them at their own doors: But at last, he sparks out, and to shut the door of trade, to all others, but himself, and a few more, who peradventure have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94198:7"/> enough to trade with, or at least uncontroulable credit, he recommends the <hi>Jewish Law</hi> against all Usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, knowing well, none will lend money <hi>Gratis,</hi> Pag. 16.</p>
            <p>This being the substance of the discourse, though I shal make answer to every particular in order, It will not be amiss, first to observe, that he makes use of the abuse of <hi>Interest,</hi> which no man pleads for (that being out of doors) to overthrow the profitable, moderate use of it, as in his instancing in <hi>Audleys</hi> observation of 100 <hi>l.</hi> at 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> which no man speaks for, and his annexing a discourse against <hi>Interest,</hi> writ in 1621. when it was at 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> Indeavouring thereby to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a belief, that the Gentleman who writ that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, was of his mind (who is for bringing <hi>Interest</hi> to 3 <hi>per Cent.</hi> and indeed to nothing) whereas it may be supposed, the Author of that book was contented with having it at 8 <hi>per Cent.,</hi> because within four years after it was brought to that rate, and that otherwise, he would have writ further, It being probable, that he might live till after four years.</p>
            <p>Thus having premised these observations, I come to make answer to his affertions, and his reasons for them, and beginning with the first, I deny, <hi>That the lowness of</hi> Interest, <hi>is the cause of riches,</hi> and affirm it to be <hi>only the effects of them;</hi> for if otherwise, every Country, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in their power to be rich, would certainly make themselves so by a low Interest stated by Law, no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple desiring poverty rather than riches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> if the lowness of <hi>Interest,</hi> were not the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of riches, in <hi>Holland</hi> they might take as much <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> as they could get, there being no Law against it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94198:8"/> but their riches, plenty of money, and reallity of secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, is the true reason why they can get no more than 3 or 4 <hi>per Cent.</hi> in all other parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is with money in <hi>Holland</hi> and all other parts (in point of <hi>Interest</hi>) as it is in the Exchange with us, the more money there is, and fewer takers, the lower is the Exchange, and when we have more lenders then borrowers <hi>Interest</hi> will be low without a law for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I confess, that the lowness or highness of <hi>Interest,</hi> in any Country, is a certain mark of its riches, or poverty; but though he would have this to be an argument for him, it is against him, and for me, who maintains, <hi>the natural lowness of</hi> Interest, <hi>to be the</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects <hi>of riches,</hi> for that which he must prove, to make good his assertion, is, that any Country in the world, was ever from a poor &amp; low condition, while <hi>Interest</hi> was at 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> made rich, by bringing it to 4 or 3. <hi>per Cent.</hi> by a law which I know is not to be done, nor, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, to be shewed, that any Country in the world, did ever state <hi>Interest</hi> by a law under 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that by a common consent of Nations, that sum is accounted indifferent to be imposed betwixt the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower and Lender, and may spare me any further la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of proving the equallity of 6 <hi>per Cent.</hi> as to a sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Interest;</hi> For the Improvement of Land in <hi>England,</hi> which he instanceth in, if there be any such as to rents (as betwixt rents and value he doth not distinguish, but seems sometimes to mean the one and sometimes the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) it is strange to me, for some of my Relations and Acquaintance do to their grief and sorrow find their lands fallen in rents below what they yeilded fifty or six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years agoe; and this is not their case alone, but I fear, setting aside some trading places, the condition of the Nation in general, yet if it were as he supposeth,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94198:8"/> it were no argument for him, because it might be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood to proceed from the effects of an equal Interest, after the falling of it from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> which no man pleads against, but to argue from one extream to another, is a bad argument, as to argue, that because ten <hi>per cent.</hi> by Law was prejudicial to the Nation, and six <hi>per cent.</hi> which is moderate, is more beneficial; therefore (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any proofs) three <hi>per cent.</hi> is best of all, is no less then still begging the question; but how confidently soever he affirms the advancement in price of Land in <hi>England,</hi> to have been great, since the bringing down of Interest, from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> which was in <hi>Anno</hi> 1651. those that have had Lands to sell, never found any such thing, but on the contrary, lower since. And if we have not experience of the rise of Land, since Interest was fallen from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> which I do as positively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, we have not, as he doth that we have; how out of all proportion is he, in concluding, that no sooner a Law for bringing Interest from six to four <hi>per cent.</hi> shall be made, then every <hi>Nobleman</hi> and <hi>Gentleman</hi> may write for 50, 100. upon all that he hath, reckoning his Land at 30. years purchase at least; but such extravigant passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may very well call in question all that he saith, as proceeding from design.</p>
            <p>As to the improvement of <hi>Ireland,</hi> if there be any thing to be bragged of there, as I fear there is not, much, though he brings it in, Page 8. as if it should make for him, when considered, it doth not at all, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I understand his meaning, in quoting the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Page 8. to prove the benefit of a low Interest, and quoting it again in Page 9. to prove the mischief of a high Interest, which are contradictions; but indeed <hi>Ireland,</hi> being an extraordinary case, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94198:9"/> it is newly freed from the destroying sword, it cannot argue much, either for or against six <hi>per cent.</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had been best let alone.</p>
            <p>The instancing in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> for paying ten and twelve <hi>per cent.</hi> Interest, is not to the point, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such sums being the abuse and excess of Interest, is no argument against six <hi>per cent,</hi> which is not so, nor for four or three <hi>per cent.</hi> which being stated by a Law, would be an extream on the other hand; but he is still as well mistaken in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where thy pay but eight <hi>per cent.</hi> as in other things.</p>
            <p>In his affirming, that the Merchants Estates, upon the Exchange, were from <hi>Anno</hi> 1600. to <hi>Anno</hi> 1635. (which he saith was but ten years after the bringing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest from ten to eight <hi>per cent.</hi>) increased <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>one,</hi> (Pag. 7.) he deals not plainly; for though he takes in 35 <hi>years</hi> for this Increase; he pens it, as if he would have the increase understood, to be in ten <hi>years,</hi> whereas his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation ought to have been, of the riches of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1625. when the abatement was first made, and what from that time, to <hi>Anno</hi> 1635. the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease was but as to his asserting, a second increase, in Merchants Estates: he there speaks plainly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, in the same Page 7. that from the fall of Interest from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> which was in <hi>Anno</hi> 1651. to the time of his writing his Book, <hi>Anno</hi> 1667. There was such another Increase as <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>one,</hi> wherein he is more out of proportion, then in his doubling of Noble and Gentlemens Estates, so soon as the Law for abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Interest is made: for I think, I may with more reason affirm, that <hi>Anno</hi> 1651. there were more Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants upon the Exchange of 10000 l. Estates, then there is now; but I believe, that for two or three years
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94198:9"/> after the fall of Interest from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> our Merchants increased in their Estates; but the cause be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, the effect ceased, and after that, they grew worse and worse.</p>
            <p>For the Instance he brings from <hi>Audley,</hi> it doth not concern the question in hand, because it is supposing Interest at ten <hi>per cent.</hi> which every man abominates: And for the <hi>Sugar-Bakers</hi> Case, there being so many circumstances in it, as would be too tedious; I will only answer it with another Case, That from <hi>Italy,</hi> where he saith Interest is at three <hi>per cent.</hi> we (where Interest is at six <hi>per cent.</hi>) fetch the <hi>Silk</hi> that makes our <hi>Silk-stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> which we carry back thither, and which we sell cheaper there, then our <hi>English</hi> Stocking-Weavers, who lives there, can or will afford those <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey make there; and this I speak by experience.</p>
            <p>Now what hath been said, being sufficient (I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) to answer and disprove the two first assertions, that the bare bringing down of Interest to four <hi>per cent.</hi> will alone increase the Trade and riches of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that immediately after passing a Law for it, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Noble and Gentleman, may write his Estate dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I come unto the third assertion, <hi>That the matter in</hi> England, <hi>is prepared for an abatement of Interest, and that it cannot be long obstructed, for that nature will have its course.</hi> If the Gentleman had given any reason for this assertion, or explained what he meant by that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I should have either allowed or denyed them; but since he hath not, I shall give him my definition of such a preparation, and leave it to him to mend: where there is such a preparation, I judge there must necessarily be more people then the Land, to Till and manage ground as it is in <hi>Holland;</hi> for except Land be high, Interest cannot
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94198:10"/> be low; and I challenge any man, to shew me where Land is high, and the Country not populous; and though we cannot be said to be very thin of people, we have surely more Land then people, as the Northern and other parts of the Kingdom sheweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To such a preparation, I conceive, a full and great Trade is necessary; for without plenty of money Interest cannot be low, no more then Land high, without plenty of people; and without Trade, we cannot abound in either money or people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To such a preparation, <hi>liberty of Conscience,</hi> together with low Customs, <hi>is necessary,</hi> to incourage our own people to manage and Till our Land (without being in fear of hard imprisonment) and strangers to come in and trade with us; many more circumstances are needful to such a natural preparation as <hi>I. C.</hi> speaks of; yet whether we are under these circumstances, I refer to every mans Judgement. And having now said (I presume) enough to his three assertions, because I find him at a loss for the reason of our great Trade at present, to what we had anciently, which I suppose puts him upon mistakes, I will help him the best I can in it, and give him, <hi>First,</hi> those reasons which I judge was the cause of our want of Trade anciently; <hi>Secondly,</hi> of the increasing of it since 1545. and 1600. and, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the way to increase it yet more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Not long before <hi>Anno</hi> 1545. all Christendom may be said to have been under the bondage of the <hi>Pope,</hi> who keeping all Nations in continual contests one against an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or imployed to the Holy Land (that in the mean time he might fish in troubled waters; for by such arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices he advanced himself) the people of <hi>Europe,</hi> as they had little Trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, so they had little time to mind Trade;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94198:10"/> and especially the <hi>English,</hi> who were so ridden by the <hi>Pope,</hi> that other Nations, in reproach of them, for their slavish servilities to him, called <hi>England</hi> his Ass.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Priests, Monks, Fryars, Nuns,</hi> and other Church-men, who devoured the Land without contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting any thing to the good of mankind, were so nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that they had half, if not three parts of the Land in their hands: One may gather by the <hi>Statute of Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> which forbids their injoying any more, and which was made on purpose, lest otherwise they should have got all the Land into their hands; so that whilst such multitudes of that sort of cattel was amongst us, it was impossible for us to come forward, either in Trade or riches, and therefore it was not the want of a stated Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest that hindered our growth in Trade and riches, for we have no cause to judge our Ancestors wisdomes, as to think they were not able to discern whether we were fit for a stated <hi>Interest</hi> or no; and that if they had found us prepared for it, they would not have given it to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Our <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> were then so great, that most of the rest of the people lived idle, by depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon them, without seeking further; and where any Nation is so constituted, as our was then, they shall never come forward, either in trade or wealth, which in some degree, is (at present) the case of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and that which makes them come no better forward in the world, and not the want of a lower stated Interest, it being but eight <hi>per cent.</hi> there; for that alone, without other circumstances, would do th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m no good, but make them worse, in draining them of all their money. And these are I suppose reasons enough to shew the cause of our ancient poverty, to what it is now; and that it was not the want of a stated Interest.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94198:11"/>
            <p>As to the cause of our flourishing, since 1545 and continuing in an increase of it ever since that time, the reasons are</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Our casting off the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> with all its trompery and baggage (which hindred our prosperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) with not only dividing their Lands amongst the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry.</hi> &amp;c. but also delivering the people in general, from the yoak of the Church, incouraged them much to Industry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Statutes in <hi>Henry</hi> the 7's. time, prohibiting Noblemens Retainers, and making their Lands lyable to debts, and salable, rendered the estates of <hi>England</hi> more defusive, and forced retainers, who before lived idly by dependance upon their Masters, to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to Callings, which did consequently naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease Trade. And for this I confess my self indebted to that worthy Gentleman <hi>I. H.</hi> having it from his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the ballance of Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The discovery and Improvement of the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West-India</hi> Trades, especially our <hi>English Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the West-Indies</hi> hath been the greatest cause of our increase in trade and wealth, since 1600. for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, we formerly had our East-Indie commodities from <hi>Venice,</hi> and most over land, now we have them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly by Sea from the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> and serves them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides other parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> with the same commodities we used to have from them, as well as with <hi>West-Indie</hi> commodities, &amp; that that Trade grew naturally, and not by compulsion, we may observe, from that so soon as we got any freedom from the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nobility,</hi> a stated <hi>Interest</hi> was discovered to be useful, whereas before we were under no capacity, of making use of it, having as may be supposed little trade or money in the land; for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94198:11"/>
               <hi>An.</hi> 1545. when <hi>Interest</hi> was first limited, <hi>Henry</hi> the 8 had alienated the Church-lands, and cast off <hi>Rome,</hi> which made limiting of <hi>Interest</hi> useful to us, because the wealth of <hi>England,</hi> then begun to be defusive (and thereby trade to grow) which before it was not; and thus much I think may serve to shew, that the lessening of <hi>Interest</hi> was not the cause of our increase of trade; but the increase of trade, by other accedents, was the cause of the lessening (which before was unlimited) of <hi>Interest;</hi> and that it was lessened by stinting it by a law: was because our Ancestors who could not then (Trade being new to them) so well understand that the nature of trade is such, as will of it self bring <hi>Interest</hi> under: but because bringing <hi>Interest</hi> in those days to 10 <hi>per Cent.</hi> certain, from peradventure 12 or 14. Trade did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards increase, which without it I beleeve it would have done, the obstructions being then removed, it doth not follow, that to bring it from 6. which is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable rate to land) to 4 <hi>per Cent.</hi> will still increase trade; for if we will imitate <hi>Holland,</hi> in <hi>Interest,</hi> we must use those means as they do, which will bring it naturally low, and not to think to do that by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion with us, which with them is done by nature: They have, by the means of Trade, much more people than land; their trade makes plenty of money and people; their plenty of money, with abundance of people, makes land dear, and the dearness of land, with plenty of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, makes <hi>Interest</hi> naturally low; when we can say, that we have more people then land, which must be occasioned by Trade, which will bring plenty of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then we shall find land rise, and <hi>Interest</hi> natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly low; but to follow <hi>Holland</hi> in their natural way, by a Compulsive Law, when we have not parity of reason,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94198:12"/> we shall but hurt our selves, and give them an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in trade, by having our Trade ingrossed, into a few over-grown rich mens hands, to the excluding young men with smal stocks, and I wish the writing of this Book, hath not been done out of some such design.</p>
            <p>The way to increase trade, and thereby money, and consequently bring <hi>Interest</hi> in a natural way low, is by observing those rules practiced by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and laid down by <hi>I. C.</hi> in the beginning of his Book, and Suppliment, and here recited, with some others that might be added, but without them it can never be done, naturally, and to do it otherwise will undoe us, by bringing, as is before hinted, all trade into a few hands, and if <hi>I. C.</hi> did not intend to bring the practice of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> together with the Law for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of <hi>Interest,</hi> I wonder why he mentioned the reasons given in the begining of his Book, except he did it to shew that he would go contrary to them; the benefit of <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> is very observable, in the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> where giving it freely, they flourish exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, while the rigidnes of the <hi>Presbyters of Zeoland,</hi> and <hi>Freezeland</hi> their Neighbours, and who have I think equal conveniency for Trade with them, are mightily kept back by their narrowness in it. And now I shall say no more then recommend unto observation the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>I. C.</hi> writing: As</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> in his giving the reasons which makes Interest naturally in <hi>Holland</hi> at three <hi>per cent.</hi> and yet concluding (without any reason shewn) that a law to state interest at four or three <hi>per cent.</hi> will do the same with us, as the reasons he instanceth in doth naturally with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That he begs the question (without making any thing good) of all his three assertions, As that a sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94198:12"/> low Interest is the cause of riches, bringing only for proof, That in rich Countries Interest is low, which proves no more, then, that a low Interest is the effect of riches, wherein we had the example in 1649, 1650, 1651. when the Interest by Law being then at eight <hi>per cent.</hi> good security could have it at five. That as soon as a Law is made to bring Interest to four <hi>per cent.</hi> he bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirms, without proof, That Land will be of double value; and this he doth against the experience of the last fall of Interest, from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced no rise at all, as the sellers of Land can witness: And that the matter of <hi>England,</hi> which he affirms is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for an abatement of Interest, he makes no attempt to prove.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That he argues from one extream to another, making Instances against ten <hi>per cent.</hi> to serve for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to four and three <hi>per cent.</hi> without giving any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons why six <hi>per cent.</hi> is not an indifferent rate for Law to take notice of, and makes use of an observation of <hi>Audleys,</hi> which is a false calculation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That his calculations concerning Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Estates upon the Exchange, is so far out of all proportion, that whereas he saith, they are increased <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>one</hi> since that last fall of Interest from eight to six <hi>per cent.</hi> those that knows the Exchange best do believe they are not by much so rich now as they were in 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. when Interest was at eight <hi>per cent.</hi> a vash difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>one,</hi> and less then nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That he miserable mistakes the ground of our ancient poverty in putting, it upon the want of a low stated Interest, when it proceeded wholly from the slavery the people were in those dayes under to the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> but principally to the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94198:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> When he pretends to make inquiry whether a low in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest be truly the cause or effect of riches; he concludes, without giving one syllable of reason for it, that it is the cause of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity and riches of any Nation; and that it may be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, puts it in great letters, Page 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He saith it hath always been the policy of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Holland</hi> to keep down Interest three or four <hi>per cent.</hi> under their Neighbours, as if they did it by Law (for otherwise nature, and not policy doth it) whereas it is utterly untrue, that ever they made any Law to that end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Though his Instance in the <hi>East-Indy Companies</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king money at four <hi>per cent.</hi> be true, yet it proceeds from their generosity in paying linimen their money at any time upon a days warning, which conveniency to monied men, that lyeth in wait for good bargains, deserves a low Interest, the Company being therein little less then noble Cash keepers to monied men, giving them four <hi>per cent.</hi> more then they could make of their money, if it lay in their own Iron-chests: and though it be true, that the Company have money at four <hi>per cent.</hi> it stands not with reason that from this example men should be forced by a Law to lend money at the same rate, or not at all, where there is not a parity of reason.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> The Treatise he annexeth unto his, is as grosly mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as himself, in saying, that most of the Countries with whom we hold Commerce, doth not tollerate above six <hi>per cent.</hi> whereas I know no great trading Cities that doth limit Interest at all: <hi>Hambourge</hi> and <hi>Dantzick,</hi> which are for trade next to <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> doth not; and <hi>I. C.</hi> confesseth, that in <hi>France</hi> Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest is at seven <hi>per cent.</hi> and yet instanceth that Country for Riches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Whereas he insinuateth, that the cause of <hi>Scotlands</hi> poverty proceeds from Interest, being there at ten or twelve <hi>per cent.</hi> I am informed, that whereas formerly Interest was by law a six <hi>per cent.</hi> they have of late years judged it for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to raise it by Law to eight <hi>per cent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly</hi> and lastly, Whilst he saith, that the matter of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is so naturally prepared for an abatement of Interest, that it cannot be long obstructed, he propounds a Law to anticipate na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is against reason. And thus hoping that we shall not be led to our own distruction, by a confident imposing mistakes upon us, I have done.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94198:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>